Guide to the German newspaper clippings collection, 1900-1943 RL.00445
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
German newspaper clippings collection
1900-1943
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00445
1.3 Linear Feet
The newspaper clippings and other publications in this collection focus on political events both in Germany and abroad, in particular assassinations and political violence. They include announcements, analysis and propaganda, exhortations, and numerous political cartoons. The materials are arranged according to geographical area. Also included are political party publications relating to local, state, and national elections in Germany between 1919 and 1930, as well as items relating to international events between 1900 and 1930. The collection also includes a small series of Nazi propaganda dating from 1939 to 1943. Closely related to the German Broadsides collection.
Approximately 251 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The German Newspaper Clippings Collection is an artificial collection acquired or assembled by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library around 1948.
Collection Overview
The newspaper clippings and other publications in this collection focus on political events both in Germany and abroad, in particular assassinations and political violence. While most items are small in size, there is a group of oversize items consist of whole pages taken from issues. Content includes announcements, analysis and propaganda, exhortations, and numerous political cartoons. The materials are arranged according to geographical area. Also included are political party publications relating to local, state, and national elections in Germany between 1919 and 1930, as well as items relating to international events between 1900 and 1930, particularly in Russia and China.
The collection also includes a small series of Nazi propaganda and other ephemera, dating from 1939 to 1943, containing three certificates, two blank sheets of letterhead, and a Nazi-produced newsletter for a United States audience, as well as a set of typescripts (in English) of undated German propaganda.
Closely related to the German Broadsides Collection.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series: Campaign Publications and Political Brochures, International Politics and Political Violence, International Relations and Movements, Nazi Propaganda, and Other Topics.
Related Material
German newspapers in the Rubenstein Library
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
German Broadsides Collection, 1870-1990, bulk 1920s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Germany -- History -- 20th century; Leipzig (Germany) -- History; China -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1918-1933; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons; Berlin (Germany) -- History; Political parties -- Germany -- History; Nazi propaganda -- Germany; Elections -- Germany -- 1920-1940; Political parties -- Germany -- History -- 20th century; Russia -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Kommunistische Partei Deutschlands; Deutschnationale Volkspartei; Deutsche Demokratische Partei
- Campaign Publications and Political Brochures, 1919-1930 and undated; 2 boxes and items in oversize folder
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains clippings and other publications relating to local, state, and national elections, mostly from the Socialist, Communist, German Democratic, and German National People's political parties, with some material from the Center Party and other interest groups. Other items relate more to political issues generally. Many of them originated from German newspapers and election newspapers printed and distributed by political parties. Arranged chronologically.
  - Worte und Taten! Seit 2 Monaten herrscht die Sozialdemokratie über Deutschland. Was hat sie uns gebracht? Leipziger Allgemeine Zeitung, no. 12 (Jan. 13, 1919): 7 (Oversize-box 1)
  - Zeitstimmen. Worum handelt es bei der Trennung von Kirche und Staat? (Evangelische Preßverband für Deutschland, Berlin, 1919) (Box 1)
  - Karl Gareis als Mensch, Mitteilungsblatt der U.S.P. München, vol. 1, no. 1 (June 13, 1921) (Box 1)
  - Geplante Maßnahmen der Reichsregierung Münchner Neueste Nachrichten (June 25, 1922) (Oversize-box 1)
  - An das deutsche Proletariat! Arbeiter, Angestellte und Beamte! Sächsische Arbeiter Zeitung, vol. 2, no. 1 (July 28, 1922) (Box 1)
  - Deutschnationale Nachrichten für das Vogtland (German National People's Party, Plauen, Nov. 1922) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Deutsches Witzblatt. Nieder mit der Zinsknechtschaft! (Richard Kunze, 1924) (Box 1)
  - Hallo! Die große Revue. Ein deutsches Bilderbuch (Socialist Party, Leipzig, 1924) (Box 1)
  - Der neue Reichstag. 'Was für zwei Kerle haben sie mir da wieder auf den Rücken gesetzt!' Simplicissimus, vol. 29, no. 7 (May 12, 1924) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Deutsche Volkspartei Wahlzeitung (German People's Party, Kiel, 1924) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Arbeiterfrauen. Alle Macht geht vom Volke aus.... (Communist Party, Berlin, 1924) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Asyl für Erwerbslose. An alle Erwerbslosen, Kurz- und Notstandsarbeiter Deutschlands! (Communist Party, Berlin, 1924) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Sowjet-Rußland. Berichte der bürgerlichen Wissenschaftler Prof. Dr. Obst--Hannover, Dr. Grabowsky--Berlin als Augenzeugen (Berlin, 1924) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Zwölf Monate demokratischer Politik (Rede des Reichsbankpräsidenten Dr. Schacht) (German Democratic Party, Leipzig, 1924) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Wen soll ich wählen? (German Social Party, Dresden, 1924) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Der rote Präsident. Wahlzeitung der Kommunistischen Partei Deutschlands (Bezirk Westsachsen) zur Präsidentenwahl (Communist Party, Mar. 21, 1925) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Sachsens Wahlspruch. Alle Schaffenden wählen am 12. Mai Liste 1 (Socialist Party, Dresden, 1928) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - German People's Party campaign newspaper, Frankfurt, May 20, 1928 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Weckruf. Aufklärungsschrift für die Bevölkerung Schleswig-Holsteins (Socialist Party, Dec. 1930) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Liste 4 Wahl-Zeitung der KPD Südbayern (Communist Party, 1930) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Der Staatsbürger. Blätter der Deutschen Staatspartei zu den Reichstagswahlen (German State Party, circa 1933) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Wahlzeitung für Niederschlesien (Socialist Party, 1932) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Voraussagungen die sich erfüllen! Arbeiter-Illustrierte Zeitung, vol. 9, no. 4 (Jan. 22, 1930) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Karl Gareis, der deutsche Matteotti. Ermordet am 9. Juni 1921, Leipziger Volkszeitung, vol. 35, no. 131 (June 7, 1928) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Das Rote Banner. Wahlzeitung der Kommunistischen Partei, Bezirk Hessen-Frankfurt (1928) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Schleswig-Holsteinische Wählerzeitung (1928) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Kämpfende Jugend. Sonderdruck der Sächsischen Arbeiter-Zeitung (Communist Party, 1929) (Oversize-box 1)
  - Die rote Peitsche. Wahlbeilage der kommunistischen Ruhrpresse (Essen, 1930) (Oversize-box 1)
- International Politics and Political Violence, 1900-1930; 3 boxes and items in oversize box
  Contains clippings arranged according to geographical subject matter, with material from Europe, Asia, the Middle East, South America, and North America. The majority of the clippings date from 1928 to 1930, though several come from 1900. They originated from newspapers and journals published around Germany (including Leipzig, Kiel, Berlin, Munich, Baden-Baden, Halle, Greifswald), and present both leftist and conservative viewpoints, focusing on political events, in particular assassinations and political violence. Numerous political cartoons are included. A cardfile with entries corresponding to the clippings is found at the end of the series.
  - Afghanistan (Box 1)
  - Bulgaria (Box 1)
  - China (Box 1)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 1)
  - England (Box 1)
  - France (Box 1)
  - Germany (Box 1)
  - Greece (Box 1)
  - Hungary (Box 1)
  - India (Box 2)
  - Japan (Box 2)
  - Lithuania (Box 2)
  - Poland (Box 2)
  - Romania (Box 2)
  - Russia (Box 2)
  - South America (Bolivia-Paraguay) (Box 2)
  - Syria (Box 2)
  - United States (Box 2)
  - Yugoslavia (Box 2)
  - Czechoslovakia (Oversize-box 1)
  - England (Box 2)
  - France (Box 2)
  - Japan (Box 2)
  - Lithuania (Box 2)
  - Romania (Box 2)
  - Russia (Box 2)
  - Turkey (Box 2)
  - Clippings index (cardfile) (Box 3)
- International Relations and Movements, 1925-1930 and undated; 1 box and items in oversize folder
  Contains material relating to the political situation in China and international peace, workers, and anti-imperialism movements. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Anti-Imperialism, Worker, and Peace Movements
    - Die rote Front. 1. Sonderausgabe der SAZ. zum Antikriegstag am 2. August in Leipzig (Leipzig, 1925) (Oversize-folder 1)
  - China
    - Extrablatt. Voller Sieg der Sowjetunion im Fernen Osten, Sächsische Arbeiter-Zeitung (Nov. 28, 1929) (Oversize-box 1)
    - Sowjetbanner über Kwangsi, Die Rote Fahne 34 (Feb. 9, 1930) (Oversize-box 1)
    - Partisankrieg in China, Sächsische Arbeiter Zeitung 10, no. 117 (May 21, 1930) (Oversize-box 1)
    - Articles about China in Die kapitalistische Wirtschaft. Ständiger Wirtschaftsteil des "Kampf" Der Kampf. Organ für Gewerkschaftsfragen u. soziale Fragen vol. 1, no. 5 (July 28, 1930) (Oversize-box 1)
- Nazi Propaganda and Ephemera, 1930s-1943; 1 box and items in oversize folder
  Domestic and international Nazi propaganda, including certificates, letterhead, a newspaper clipping, and a Nazi-produced newsletter for America. Also includes 85 pro-Nazi articles, most of unknown origin, in English (possibly translated from German), on various topics, apparently from the 1930s-early 1940s.
  - Leistungsbescheinigung (coupon to be exchanged for a gas mask); with map of occupied Poland on back, Hauptamt für Volkswohlfahrt, Oct. 10, 1939 (Box 2)
  - American Views, Supplement to News from Germany, Nov. 1939 (Box 2)
  - Urkunde im Namen des Führers danke ich […] für die Spende zur Sammlung von Wollpelz und Wintersachen für die Front (Reich Propaganda Leader and Reich Minister for People's Enlightenment and Propaganda, Joseph Goebbels, Christmas 1941, 2 copies) (Box 2)
  - Wie aus dem Boden gewachsen…. Berliner Illustrierte Zeitung, Oct. 28, 1943 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - National Socialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei NS-Frauenschaft Kreis Bonn, Gau Köln-Aachen (letterhead, blank, 2 copies) (Box 2)
  - Nazi Propaganda typescripts, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Other Items, 1919 and undated, 1 folder
  - Vergessen, Kladderadatsch, no. 4 (periodical, 1919) (Box 2)
  - Ein schones Jesu Lied, undated (Box 2)
  - Ein Joseph Lied, undated (Box 2)